<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mcqs>
	<options>
		<incorrectAnswers>
			<incorrectAnswer node="Options" item="1" dataIndex="0">Steatosis, which usually is macrovesicular but may be microvesicular or mixed</incorrectAnswer>
			<incorrectAnswer node="Options" item="2" dataIndex="0">Mixed, mild, lobular inflammation; scattered PMN leucocytes as well as mononuclear cells</incorrectAnswer>
			<incorrectAnswer node="Options" item="3" dataIndex="0">Hepatocellular Ballooning; most apparent near steatotic liver cells</incorrectAnswer>
			<incorrectAnswer node="Options" item="4" dataIndex="0">Perisinusoidal fibrosis\n\nPerisinusoidal fibrosis</incorrectAnswer>
		</incorrectAnswers>
		<correctAnswers>
			<correctAnswer node="Options" item="0" dataIndex="0">Sclerosing hyaline necrosis;veno-occlusive lesions;perivenular fibrosis;phlebosclerosis</correctAnswer>
		</correctAnswers>
	</options>
	
	<background>Question ID 5701</background>
	<question>Which of the following is considered unusual as a histological finding of NASH in a liver biopsy? </question>
	
	<core>Steatosis</core>
	<explanation>Steatosis. The type of steatosis that predominates in adults and in children is macrovesicular, with a single droplet that results in nuclear eccentricity because it occupies the entire cell cytoplasm or with several smaller but well-defined droplets within the cytoplasm. Special stains for fat are not required for microscopic detection of macrovesicular steatosis; studies that use oil red O for steatosis estimates often report much greater amounts than those found with standard hematoxylin-eosin (H + E) staining. On the other hand, it is not uncommon for there to be a mixture of hepatocytes with combinations of large single droplets and multiple small droplets. Clusters of hepatocytes with intracytoplasmic delicate septations due to microvesicular steatosis may also be present. Ballooning. Hepatocyte ballooning, a feature denoting cellular injury, is considered a required feature of NASH in adults. Ballooning is a feature that denotes progressive NAFL.The term applies to enlarged, swollen-appearing hepatocytes; the affected cells are often intermixed in areas of steatosis and, in classic steatohepatitis, in the perivenular regions. Hepatocellular ballooning is most commonly noted in regions of H + E-detectable perisinusoidal fibrosis. Ballooned hepatocytes are most easily noted when they contain MH (either typical or poorly formed). Hepatocyte ballooning is a structural manifestation of microtubular disruption and severe cell injury and is not unique to alcoholic or nonalcoholic steatohepatitis but is likely a representation of cells undergoing lytic necrosis. Inflammation. Lobular inflammation is usually mild but is integral to the diagnosis of steatohepatitis. Studies of pathogenesis have delineated or proposed numerous proinflammatory cytokines involved in the progressive lipotoxicity of NAFLD and NASH.A characteristic form of lobular inflammation in which PMN leukocytes are a component is mixed.  Fibrosis.The necessity of fibrosis for a diagnosis in NASH is an area of discussion. The characteristic pattern of fibrosis that distinguishes non-cirrhotic steatohepatitis (alcoholic and nonalcoholic) from other forms of chronic liver disease is the initial deposition of collagen in perisinusoidal spaces perisinusoidal fibrosis. When dense, the fibrosis may be observed by H + E, but in all cases it is readily detected with specific histochemical stains for collagen, such as Masson trichrome. A source of inconsistency in observations of fibrosis in published studies of a variety of liver diseases is derived from the different uses of histochemical stains to detect collagen; Sweet reticulin and picrosirius red stains highlight more types of collagen that are present in the sinusoids of the liver than the Masson stain, and use of these stains may result in observation of greater involvement than detected by Masson. Mallory's Hyaline. The intracellular ropy inclusions known as MH, a recognized histological hallmark of alcoholic hepatitis, are also noted in zone 1 hepatocytes in chronic cholestatic liver diseases, copper toxicity, and certain drugs (griseofulvin in mice and phospholipidosis-associated amiodarone toxicity) and in hepatocellular proliferative lesions, focal nodular hyperplasia, and HCC.In alcoholic hepatitis, MH is most commonly found in zone 3 in ballooned or apoptotic hepatocytes; in nonalcoholic steatohepatitis, MH may be "poorly formed" cytoplasmic aggregates noted in zone 3 ballooned hepatocytes. Other Lesions of Nash. Megamitochondria may be observed in hepatocytes in NASH; the relative frequency of this finding has not been rigorously studied. Megamitochondria appear as rounded or needle-shaped intracytoplasmic inclusions. When rounded, they are approximately the size of a red blood cell. In one study of alcoholic hepatitis, megamitochondria were identified in combination with mixed steatosis as a marker of progression to fibrosis] Ultrastructural studies of human liver in NAFLD and NASH have documented a variety of structural lesions, including paracrystalline inclusions, loss of cristae and multilamellar membranes.As opposed to alcoholic liver disease, however, mitochondrial DNA deletion is uncommon in NASH. In summary, adult NASH is characterized by a combination of lesions in which steatosis, ballooning, lobular inflammation, and perisinusoidal fibrosis are the primary components of interest. Minimal criteria for diagnosis vary in terms of the specific combination of lesions. Consideration not often discussed is that variances in histological lesions may actually reflect variances in the individual patient's metabolic status at the time of the biopsy.</explanation>
</mcqs>